<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/assets/xslt/atom.xslt" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="/assets/css/atom.css" ?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<id>https://www.fedarch.org/</id>
	<title>FAIMS Project</title>
	<updated>2020-03-31T19:50:33+11:00</updated>

	<subtitle>FAIMS provides tools for the collection of born-digital field data through to archiving for any research discipline, workflow, ontology, and standard.</subtitle>

	
		
		<author>
			
				<name>Brian Ballsun-Stanton</name>
			
			
				<email>brian@fedarch.org</email>
			
			
				<uri>http://drbbs.org</uri>
			
		</author>
	

	<link href="https://www.fedarch.org/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link href="https://www.fedarch.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />

	<generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator>

	
		<entry>
			<id>https://www.fedarch.org/news/Perachora/</id>
			<title>Perachora project puts FAIMS Mobile to test</title>
			<link href="https://www.fedarch.org/news/Perachora/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Perachora project puts FAIMS Mobile to test" />
			<updated>2020-02-02T00:00:00+11:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>adela</name>
					
					
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>Macquarie University team of archaeologists use FAIMS to record the environs of Heraion sanctuary in Greece</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="https://www.fedarch.org/news/Perachora/">&lt;p&gt;Macquarie University team of archaeologists and students spent January in Greece surveying the ancient sanctuary of Hera and its environs using FAIMS Mobile platform. The Perachora Peninsula Archaeological Project led by Susan Lupack of Macquarie Univeristy in collaboration with Panagiota Kasimi, the Ephor of the Ephorate of Antiquities of Corinth, aims to map the standing features around the photogenic site and explore the past human activity in the peninsula throught the long-term. Joined by Shawn Ross and 15 students, and Adela Sobotkova and Petra Janouchova from Aarhus University, the team used two FAIMS modules to record surface artefacts densities and standing features, and photogrammetry to make digital models of the best preserved structures. With the help of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/FAIMS/Perachora-2020&quot;&gt;Feature recording module&lt;/a&gt;, an on-the-spot assembled variation of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/FAIMS/burial&quot;&gt;TRAP burial module&lt;/a&gt;, the students followed historical maps of the Heraion environs and recorded 108 standing walls, masonry structures, tombs, roads, cisterns and shafts. With the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/FAIMS/trap-gridded-survey&quot;&gt;grid-survey module&lt;/a&gt;, they scrambled through forests, olive groves and scrubby scliffs at 5 m intervals to document 16 ha of terrain, documenting a total of 22,817 artefacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each team used the k1 Shield Nvidia Android tablet with bluetooth GPS to document archaeological realities. The survey-grid module allowed them to document the density of 12 different classes of artefacts at 5 by 5 m spatial granularity, an ideal setup for systematic urban-level survey. All teams kept also a paper back up with handheld GPS and DSLR cameras to ensure redundancy.  The progress was slow due both to vegetation and high density of artefacts, but it was rewarded by gorgeous views, painted pottery, and the great pleasure of downloading clean and complete data at the end of the day. Thanks to the low-power FAIMS server kit and technical skills among the team, the sporadic electricity and nonexistent internet were no show-stoppers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, Petra and Adela were thrilled as the modules exceeded their expectations. Students learnt that no bushes can stop them and grew stronger thanks to the steep learning curve (for their reflections see their &lt;a href=&quot;https://ancient-history-blog.mq.edu.au/PPAP-blog-final&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;). Even photogrammetry under Shawn’s direction, although plagued by technical challenges, produced fantastic results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are ready for the next season!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>

			
				<category term="News" />
			
			

			<published>2020-02-02T00:00:00+11:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>https://www.fedarch.org/news/YesWeCan/</id>
			<title>Printing Labels on the Go</title>
			<link href="https://www.fedarch.org/news/YesWeCan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Printing Labels on the Go" />
			<updated>2018-05-04T00:00:00+10:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>adela</name>
					
					
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>Tao River Project adds mobile label printing to their FAIMS module in 2018</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="https://www.fedarch.org/news/YesWeCan/">&lt;p&gt;The Tao River Archaeological Project in China has been using FAIMS to record their excavation and sampling activities since 2016. Installing mobile apps on devices in China is not without its challenges, given the inaccessibility of Google (and therefore Play Store) in the country. With meticulous preparation and great patience on the part of project director, Dr Rowan Flad from Harvard University, we have solved this and many other issues. This year Dr Flad wants to connect their field module to a mobile barcode printer to facilitate the production of human- and machine-readable labels. We are, therefore, expanding their FAIMS module to connect to a mobile Zebra printer over the Bluetooth and produce such labels on the basis of existing records at the push of a button. All of the development is happening remotely, with our team in Sydney working with a Zebra printer kindly loaned by the Gamma Solutions, while Dr Flad communicates his needs. He will harness his own mobile printer to test the new functionality after he finishes spring semester in Cambridge, Massachusetts. 
The success of deploying digital tools in the field depends on the upfront investment of effort by the field researcher into discovering their needs and testing the initial prototypes. The Tao River Project team has demonstrated that digital tools are a priority and the increasingly sophisticated module is a testimony to their successful co-development with FAIMS.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>

			
				<category term="News" />
			
			

			<published>2018-05-04T00:00:00+10:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>https://www.fedarch.org/news/BlueMountainsOne/</id>
			<title>Mapping the lost mining settlements in the Blue Mountains</title>
			<link href="https://www.fedarch.org/news/BlueMountainsOne/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mapping the lost mining settlements in the Blue Mountains" />
			<updated>2018-04-27T00:00:00+10:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>adela</name>
					
					
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>Macquarie University students use FAIMS to record historical heritage around the Ruined Castle</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="https://www.fedarch.org/news/BlueMountainsOne/">&lt;p&gt;Ruined Castle, 27 April 2018: It is fall break at Macquarie University. Some students choose to rest or study for exams, others have chosen to spend a week wading through the ferns in the Blue Mountains World Heritage Area in search of the remains of a 19th century shale mining village. Under the direction of Bec Parkes of Lantern Heritage and Shawn Ross of Macquarie University, the team of seven history and archaeology students have been getting up at 6 am to hike down the Golden Staircase and conduct archaeological survey. 
Once on site, students break up into teams of two and systematically scrutinize the ground looking for modifications on boulders, patterns in collapsed stones, scatters of glass and ceramics that indicate the location of miners’ huts. Dozens of such features are hiding under the dense canopy mere meters of the Ruined Castle treck. Upon discovery students record the location digitally, using Android tablets to capture coordinates from external GPS, and describing feature characteristics, such as materials, dimensions, finds and interpretations. All features are photographed and sketched, keeping all records integrated on the tablet. A flag is left on the ground for the official project photographer. In five days of work, students progress from knowing the word ‘survey’ to recognising and digitally recording over 250 historical features. Negotiating rugged terrain, and climbing the equivalent of 73 flights of stairs each day has been not only a fantastic way to spend the holidays, but a meaningful undertaking that generated an analysis-ready dataset that illustrates the history of industrial settlement in the Blue Mountains.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>

			
				<category term="News" />
			
			

			<published>2018-04-27T00:00:00+10:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>https://www.fedarch.org/news/CAA_2017_Spring_Institute/</id>
			<title>FAIMS at CAA 2017 Spring Institute</title>
			<link href="https://www.fedarch.org/news/CAA_2017_Spring_Institute/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FAIMS at CAA 2017 Spring Institute" />
			<updated>2017-09-22T00:00:00+10:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Robert Haubt</name>
					
					
						<email>robert@fedarch.org</email>
					
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>FAIMS attended the CAA Australasia Spring Institute</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="https://www.fedarch.org/news/CAA_2017_Spring_Institute/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FAIMS attended the first Computer Applications &amp;amp; Qualitative Methods in Archaeology Spring Institute for Australasia from the 3rd – 8th September 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.fedarch.org/images/2017-09-22-Kioloa-I.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ANU Coastal Campus, Kioloa, NSW&quot; /&gt; ANU Coastal Campus, Kioloa, NSW&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event was held at the Australian National University’s Kioloa Coastal Campus and was jointly organised by the CAA Australasia and the Department of Archaeology, University Sydney. Participants came from all over Australia and New Zealand to discuss the use of digital technologies in archaeology and looked at recent advancements in the field. The event included sessions on Spatial Data Collectio, Terrestrial Remote Sensing, Geospatial and Geophysical Data with sessions on knowledge management systems and digital workflows and archaeological repositiories given by Robert Haubt and Shawn Ross from the FAIMS Project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.fedarch.org/images/2017-09-22-Kioloa-III.png&quot; alt=&quot;Drone Workshop with Dr.Yann Tristan; FAIMS workshop with A/Prof. Shawn Ross&quot; /&gt; Drone Workshop with Dr.Yann Tristan; FAIMS workshop with A/Prof. Shawn Ross&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information on the CAA Australasia event can be found here &lt;a href=&quot;http://au.caa-international.org/spring-institute/&quot;&gt;CAA Australasia 2017 Spring Institute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank Dr. Ian Johnson from the University of Sydney for organising this event.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>

			
				<category term="News" />
			
			

			<published>2017-09-22T00:00:00+10:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>https://www.fedarch.org/news/Streamwatch_Australian_Museum/</id>
			<title>FAIMS talks to Citizen Science Project Streamwatch</title>
			<link href="https://www.fedarch.org/news/Streamwatch_Australian_Museum/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FAIMS talks to Citizen Science Project Streamwatch" />
			<updated>2017-08-30T00:00:00+10:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Robert Haubt</name>
					
					
						<email>robert@fedarch.org</email>
					
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>Streamwatch citizen science project at the Australian Museum</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="https://www.fedarch.org/news/Streamwatch_Australian_Museum/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June FAIMS had a chance to sit down with Gregory McDonald from Streamwatch at the Australian Museum to talk about using FAIMS Mobile for their citizen science project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Streamwatch is a citizen science water quality monitoring program that empowers community groups to monitor and protect the health of local waterways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find out more about Streamwatch visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://australianmuseum.net.au/streamwatch&quot;&gt;Streamwatch, Australian Museum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/twCStFgKbcU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to find out more about Streamwatch or our FAIMS Mobile solutions please contact us at enquires@fedarch.org.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>

			
				<category term="News" />
			
			

			<published>2017-08-30T00:00:00+10:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>https://www.fedarch.org/news/FAIMS_wins_ideation_challenge_for_data_capture_app/</id>
			<title>FAIMS wins Ideation Challenge</title>
			<link href="https://www.fedarch.org/news/FAIMS_wins_ideation_challenge_for_data_capture_app/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FAIMS wins Ideation Challenge" />
			<updated>2017-08-30T00:00:00+10:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Robert Haubt</name>
					
					
						<email>robert@fedarch.org</email>
					
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>FAIMS wins DataApp: A Mobile App Framework for Field Data Capture Challenge</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="https://www.fedarch.org/news/FAIMS_wins_ideation_challenge_for_data_capture_app/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are happy to announce that FAIMS has won the Ideation Challenge focusing on identifying robust and efficient software architecture concepts and software technologies for development of the desired Field Data Capture app framework. The Ideation Challenge forms Stage 1 of the three-stage &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.challenge.gov/challenge/dataapp-a-mobile-app-framework-for-field-data-capture-stage-1/&quot;&gt;DataApp: A Mobile App Framework for Field Data Capture &lt;/a&gt; Challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge was put forward by The Bureau of Reclamation, in collaboration with the U.S. Geological Survey and is seeking development of an application framework to support electronic data collection and capture using mobile devices across a diverse range of data collection situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge is looking for applications that provide a flexible, extensible, and open source framework to enable future improvement and development of added features by a community of app developers and users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to find out more about the FAIMS Project or our FAIMS Mobile solutions please contact us at enquires@fedarch.org.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>

			
				<category term="News" />
			
			

			<published>2017-08-30T00:00:00+10:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>https://www.fedarch.org/news/FAIMS-mobile-can-now-print-labels/</id>
			<title>FAIMS mobile app can now print QR code and labels</title>
			<link href="https://www.fedarch.org/news/FAIMS-mobile-can-now-print-labels/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FAIMS mobile app can now print QR code and labels" />
			<updated>2017-05-31T00:00:00+10:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Robert Haubt</name>
					
					
						<email>robert@fedarch.org</email>
					
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>print your QR codes and labels in the field from FAIMS mobile app</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="https://www.fedarch.org/news/FAIMS-mobile-can-now-print-labels/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FAIMS Mobile can now print QR codes and labels while you are in the field using the handheld &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zebra.com/ap/en/support-downloads/printers/mobile/qln420.html&quot;&gt;Zebra QLn420&lt;/a&gt; printer and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zebra.com/us/en/products/printers/mobile/p4t.html&quot;&gt;Zebra P4T&lt;/a&gt;.
FAIMS Mobile integrates the printer with a click of a button, connecting the app to the Zebra QLn420 via bluetooth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To further enhance you label printing experience we work with extra long-life thermal labels/wax ribbons, a future looking setup for collections that are looking to keep their samples for the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to thank &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gammasolutions.com/&quot;&gt;Gamma Solutions Pty. Ltd.&lt;/a&gt; at Macquarie Park for providing a test printer to our development team, to make the integration possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Wx0vSblD_bM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like to know more about how you can print your own labels and barcodes from FAIMS Mobile or have other external devices that you would like to integrate, contact our friendly team of experts at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:enquires@fedarch.org&quot;&gt;enquires@fedarch.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>

			
				<category term="News" />
			
			

			<published>2017-05-31T00:00:00+10:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>https://www.fedarch.org/news/FAIMS-Seminar-at-CAS-UOW/</id>
			<title>FAIMS Seminar Friday, 2.June 2017, Centre for Archaeological Science, University of Wollongong</title>
			<link href="https://www.fedarch.org/news/FAIMS-Seminar-at-CAS-UOW/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FAIMS Seminar Friday, 2.June 2017, Centre for Archaeological Science, University of Wollongong" />
			<updated>2017-05-31T00:00:00+10:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Robert Haubt</name>
					
					
						<email>robert@fedarch.org</email>
					
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>Seminar at the Centre for Archaeological Science, University of Wollongong</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="https://www.fedarch.org/news/FAIMS-Seminar-at-CAS-UOW/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would like to invite you to our upcoming seminar on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cas.uow.edu.au/content/groups/public/@web/@smah/documents/doc/uow232918.pdf&quot;&gt;FAIMS Project and Information infrastructure for reproducibility in field sciences&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Wollongong this Friday, 2nd June 2017 presented by A / Prof Shawn Ross and Dr Adela Sobotkova.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Date: Friday 2nd June 2017&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Time: 3:30 - 4:30 PM&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Venue: 41.G03A, UOW&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Presenter: A / Prof Shawn Ross and Dr Adela Sobotkova&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Offical Event Page: &lt;a href=&quot;http://cas.uow.edu.au/news/index.html&quot;&gt;Events: Centre for Archaeological Science, University of Wollongong&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Five years ago, FAIMS set out to build mobile software for field data capture in archaeology, improve the Australian Historical Archaeology Database (AHAD) into a general Australian archaeological data repository, and federate these components with other data services. In the interim, our focus has evolved. Today, FAIMS maintains one of the most widely used scientific mobile data collection platforms, deployed not only in archaeology but in other field sciences like geology and ecology. 
Having customised FAIMS Mobile for over two dozen projects, we gained insights into the field research data lifecycles, as well as the socio-technical challenges of applying new technologies to fieldwork.
In this presentation, we will briefly review the history of the project and the nature of the mobile data collection platform. We will discuss FAIMS experiences with transforming digital archaeological practice. Finally, we will present future plans, including development of platforms that support computational reproducibility in archaeology and archaeological sciences..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are looking forward seeing you in Wollongong!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>

			
				<category term="News" />
			
			

			<published>2017-05-31T00:00:00+10:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>https://www.fedarch.org/news/FAIMS-At-UrbanGrowth/</id>
			<title>FAIMS and Macquarie University talk Archaeology at the Discover North Parramatta Open Day</title>
			<link href="https://www.fedarch.org/news/FAIMS-At-UrbanGrowth/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="FAIMS and Macquarie University talk Archaeology at the Discover North Parramatta Open Day" />
			<updated>2017-05-30T00:00:00+10:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Robert Haubt</name>
					
					
						<email>robert@fedarch.org</email>
					
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>FAIMS at Discover North Parramatta Open Day</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="https://www.fedarch.org/news/FAIMS-At-UrbanGrowth/">&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, FAIMS and colleagues from Macquarie University went to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.urbangrowth.nsw.gov.au/projects/parramatta-north/&quot;&gt;Discover North Parramatta Open Day&lt;/a&gt; organised by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.urbangrowth.nsw.gov.au&quot;&gt;UrbanGrowth NSW&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Parramatta North Urban Transformation program will conserve, unlock and share the heritage of Parramatta North.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We met with archaeologists and students to talk ‘digital field recording’ and showcased some of our latest modules for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fedarch.org/faims-mobile/&quot;&gt;FAIMS mobile&lt;/a&gt;.
Thank you to everyone involved for a great day in Parramatta!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>

			
				<category term="News" />
			
			

			<published>2017-05-30T00:00:00+10:00</published>
		</entry>
	
		<entry>
			<id>https://www.fedarch.org/news/Introducing-Access-Coordinator/</id>
			<title>Introducing FAIMS' new Access Coordinator!</title>
			<link href="https://www.fedarch.org/news/Introducing-Access-Coordinator/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing FAIMS' new Access Coordinator!" />
			<updated>2017-05-23T00:00:00+10:00</updated>

			
				
				<author>
					
						<name>Robert Haubt</name>
					
					
						<email>robert@fedarch.org</email>
					
					
				</author>
			
			<summary>Robert is here to help you!</summary>
			<content type="html" xml:base="https://www.fedarch.org/news/Introducing-Access-Coordinator/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-new-team-member-for-faims&quot;&gt;A new team member for FAIMS!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;Robert.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Robert&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert is here to help you with your data management needs. He has joined FAIMS for the year to help with data curation needs and outreach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E-mail him at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:robert@fedarch.org&quot;&gt;robert@fedarch.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</content>

			
				<category term="News" />
			
			

			<published>2017-05-23T00:00:00+10:00</published>
		</entry>
	
</feed>